14.1 responsibility and this is the first
of our four codes.
You will find this in chapter 2 of the
code of ethics and professional conduct
and just a reminder this is not in the pin
box although it is examinable it's on a
separate document which you can download
from the PMI site free of charge.
Responsibility section 1 description of
responsibility Responsibility is our duty
to take ownership for the decisions we
make or fail to make, the actions we take
or fail to take and the consequences that
result.
Section 2 Responsibility, Aspirational
standards.
As practitioners in the global project
management community, you will see the
word practitioners is underlined in the
code.
That means the word is defined in the
glossary.
Aspirational standard number one,
we make decisions and take actions based
on the best interests of society,
public safety and the environment.
Number two, we accept only those
assignments that are consistent with our
background, experience, skills and
qualifications.
Consider the case where you are a contractor
and you've been offered a project.
It sounds interesting and you'll be well
paid for it and you don't actually have
any other work currently so this is going
to be a good match.
But as you read the
business case, you realize
it's outside your
experience in some areas.
You are thinking that you need work,
you obviously need the money, and perhaps
you might be able to
learn those extra skills
somehow or perhaps
even hire someone to help.
But the aspirational standard says you
need to be honest about your abilities and
tell your prospective
employers about the gap in
your abilities and then it
becomes their decision.
whether or not they
still want you to proceed,
you have fulfilled the
aspirational standard.
If you are an employee rather than a
contractor and your boss offers you a
contract that you don't believe you have
the skills or experience for, again,
you just have to be honest with your boss
and then it's up to the boss to decide,
maybe the boss will say, yep, that's fine,
I will see that you get that extra
training that you need, or I'll
put somebody on the team to
help you with that particular
area where you need more help.
Aspirational standard
number three, we fulfil the
commitments that we undertake,
we do what we say we will do.
Number four, when we
make errors or omissions,
we take ownership and
make corrections promptly.
When we discover errors or omissions
caused by others, we communicate them to
the appropriate body as soon as they are
discovered.
We accept accountability
for any issues resulting from
our errors or omissions or
any resulting consequences.
And in this standard, we also have to
watch out for poor quality work performed
by others and notify the appropriate
people.
Now, what other thing about that standard
is where it says that when we make errors
or omissions, we take ownership and make
corrections promptly.
I'll just put up a warning flag there that
on a project if something has gone wrong
something needs fixing you can't just fix
it everything has to go through the
integrated change control system so you
can't change something what you have to do
is raise a change control request okay so
on to number five we protect proprietary
or confidential information that has been
entrusted to us Number six, we uphold this
code and hold each other accountable to
it.
And again, the code clearly says that we
can't ignore unethical
behaviour by others.
Responsibility, mandatory standards.
As practitioners in the global project
management community, we require the
following of ourselves and our fellow
practitioners.
Regulations and legal requirements.
Number one, we inform ourselves and uphold
the policy.
policies, rules, regulations
and laws that govern
our work, professional
and volunteer activities.
2.
We report unethical or
illegal conduct to appropriate
management and if necessary
to those affected by the conduct.
Did you notice that it said
we report to management
and if necessary to those
affected by the contact?
There is nowhere that it says that we have
to approach the unethical person.
You can read the notes on the mandatory
standards for responsibility yourself,
but basically it says we don't do anything
it's illegal, including plagiarism or IP
theft, and we don't condone illegal
behaviour in others, nor do we do anything
to assist them in their
illegal behaviour, and
we must report any
illegal or unethical conduct.
Ethics complaints.
We bring violations of this code to the
attention of the appropriate
body for resolution.
We only file ethics complaints when they
are substantiated by facts.
In other words, we don't
report people if we've just heard
rumours about it or we suspect
something has gone wrong.
We need hard documented proof.
We cooperate with PMI concerning ethics
violations in a collection of related
information whether we are a complainant
or a respondent.
We also abstain from
accusing others of unethical
conduct when we do not have all the facts.
Further, we pursue disciplinary
reaction against individuals
who knowingly make false
allegations against others.
We pursue disciplinary
reaction against an individual who
retaliates against the person
raising his issues concerns.
So if someone's a whistleblower and you
find that someone is attacking him,
you've got to stand by that whistleblower.
As long as that person has
got hard documented evidence
and they're not just working
on rumour and innuendo.
That brings us to the end of 14.1
responsibility.
Next lesson is 14.2 respect.
Please read the corresponding
section of the Code of
Ethics and Proversional
Conduct before watching the video.